Guide to the Rosaleen Cahill Fitzgibbon Papers AIA.007
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Rosaleen Cahill FitzGibbon Papers
1950-1997
1970-1975
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
FitzGibbon, Rosaleen Cahill
AIA.007
7 Linear Feet in 1 record carton, 6 manuscript boxes, and 3 oversize flat box.
Rosaleen Cahill, a native of County Galway who emigrated to New York, worked in the restaurant business, managed the Irish Coffee Bar at the 1964 New York World’s Fair, and opened the Irish Pavilion in New York City. This collection contains brochures, photographs, correspondence, memoranda, event programs, newspaper clippings, and other printed material documenting her personal and professional life. In addition to recording Cahill FitzGibbon’s life, the collection displays her involvement in and importance to the New York City Irish American community through her business enterprises.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains brochures, photographs, correspondence, memoranda, event programs, newspaper clippings, and other printed material documenting the personal and professional life of Rosaleen Cahill FitzGibbon. Materials related to her career include memoranda, correspondence, photographs, and newspaper articles concerning Jim Downey’s Steakhouse, the Irish Pavilion at the 1964 New York World’s Fair, and the Irish Pavilion on East 57th Street. The materials also document Cahill FitzGibbon’s personal life, including a substantial photograph collection from holidays, vacations, private family moments, social events, and other gatherings. Most photographs are undated and have no captions. In addition to recording Cahill FitzGibbon’s life, the collection displays her involvement in and importance to the New York City Irish American community through her business enterprises.
Arrangement
Files are arranged alphabetically.
Missing Title
Series I: Revolutionary Union, 1970-1978
Series II: Revolutionary Communist Party, 1975-1982
Series III: Revolutionary Workers Headquarters, 1977-1984
Series IV: Communist Party (Marxist-Leninist), 1976-1981
Series V: Union Organizing, 1961-1988
Series VI: Subject Files, 1938-1987
Series VII: Organizational Printed Ephemera, 1938-2006
Series VIII: Buttons, 1918-1984
Series IX: Posters, 1968-1990
Series X: Artifacts and Other Ephemera, 1965-1993
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Rosaleen Cahill Fitzgibbon in February, 2000. The accession number associated with this collection is 1997.009. Framed paintings and memorabilia found in repository were added to the collection in 2015. The accession number associated with these materials is 2015.042.
Appraisal
Financial records were destroyed and discarded.
Historical/Biographical Note
Rosaleen Cahill was born in Ahascragh in County Galway, Ireland. She emigrated to New York in 1947 and began working in the restaurant business. Starting in 1953 she worked as the manager and hostess at Jim Downey's Steakhouse on Eighth Avenue in New York City, a restaurant popular with those in the theater business. Cahill also operated the restaurant's Irish Coffee Bar for many years. In 1964, Cahill managed the Irish Coffee Bar at the Irish Pavilion at the New York World's Fair. The Irish Pavilion's popularity attracted such well-known figures as Irish President Eamonn De Valera, actress Lucille Ball, and Irish singer Carmel Quinn.
Cahill married Patrick FitzGibbon in 1966 and continued to work at Downey's until 1968. That same year she and Downey opened the Irish Pavilion at East 57th Street in New York City, fulfilling their mutual dream of creating a center to "bring the authentic feeling and texture of Ireland to New York and to provide a forum for Irish artists to participate, make their contribution, and of course, find a market for their works." The Pavilion opened in June of 1968 with a gala celebration to benefit the Irish American Cultural Institute. Designed by Sean Kenny, the center featured imported foodstuffs, original artwork, books, and handcrafted woolens, glasswear, and tweeds. The shop also hosted live music four nights a week in its 100-seat restaurant and Irish Coffee Bar.
Following Downey's death, Cahill FitzGibbon took on business partner Nuala Devlin. Under their management, the Irish Pavilion remained a landmark in Manhattan for many years, attracting such musicians as The Chieftans and such artists as Beatrice Behan, Noel Sheridan, potter Philip Pearse, and weaver and basketmaker Patsy Duigan. In 1983, Cahill FitzGibbon and Devlin sold the Irish Pavilion to musician Tommy Makem (formerly of the Clancy Brothers), changing the name to Tommy Makem's Irish Pavilion.
Cahill FitzGibbon spent her retirement as an administrator at the Hunter College School of Nursing. She died in 2006.
New York World's Fair |d (1964-1965: |c New York, N.Y.); Irish Americans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social life and customs.; FitzGibbon, Rosaleen Cahill
- [1]--Gay USA, Vol. [VIII] Episode No. 4 [Air date: 7/19/1990], July 1990 (Box 7, Media ID: 231.0100)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Available for viewing by appointment only.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Format: 3/4 in. Umatic
  Duration: 00:59:00
  Scope and Content
  COMMERCIAL: OutWeek Magazine
  1. Footage of the International AIDS Conference in San Francisco
  COMMERCIAL: 550-TOOL (8665), ONLY .10 MIN - .20 FIRST MIN
  2. Phil Zwickler, Editor of PWA “Newsline”, interviews Peter Staley and Garance Frank-Ruta, of ACTUP New York, regarding the International AIDS Conference in San Francisco.
  COMMERCIAL: Gay Men’s Health Crisis (GMHC), “The Time Is Now…Get the Facts”
  3. Footage of the 13th Anniversary Celebration of MECLA. Includes footage of Christopher McCauley; Sheila James Kuehl, of the So. Calif. Womens Law Center; and Dave [Pallone], gay ex-Major League Catcher.
  COMMERCIAL: The Monster, NYC club and bar
  4. Footage of the Human Rights Campaign Fund Gala with Joan Rivers
  5. Human Rights Campaign Fund “Washington Update” regarding the Americans with Disabilities Act, which would include individuals with HIV/AIDS. Includes interview with Karen Friedman, lobbyist.
  6. Lou Maletta interviews Robert Brading, Director of the Fund for Human Dignity, regarding a recent staff walk-out. Also includes footage of David Stickle, former staff member of the Fund, discussing the recent staff walk-out.
  7. “Naming Names”: Janet Rogers, of the Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation (GLAAD), discusses a recent newspaper article regarding the Gay Officers Action League (GOAL).
  COMMERCIAL: Laser Medical Associates
  8. “Lavender Health”: Ron Vachon, Director of the Office of Gay and Lesbian Health Concerns, interviews Polly Thomas, M.D., Director of the AIDS Surveillance Unit, regarding recent HIV/AIDS-related statistics.
  9. Footage of play “Men of Manhattan”.
  COMMERCIAL: Brought to you in part by 550-TOOL (8665), ONLY .10 MIN - .20 FIRST MIN
- Ballinasloe: Inniu Agus Inde, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Abell, Kate - Pre-Press Prints, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  See also:
  Tyner, Jarvis - With Others
- Caricatures, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Castletown, Co. Kildare, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Clippings: General, 1961-1973 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1965-1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Dublin in Bloomtime, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Easter Rising, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Family Photographs, undated (Box 2)
- Family Photographs, undated (Box 3)
- Family Photographs, undated (Box 4)
- Family Photographs, undated (Box 5)
- Family Photographs, undated (Box 6)
- Family Photographs, undated (Box 7, Folder 1-9)
- Framed Paintings and Memorabilia, undated; 2015.042 (Box 9-10)
- Rosaleen Cahill FitzGibbon: Individual Photographs, undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Rosaleen Cahill FitzGibbon: Photographs With Celebrities and Political Figures, circa 1964-1976 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- The Four Courts Print, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Galway Association of New York, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Galways Men's Social and Benevolent Association of New York Banquet, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Guest Book, 1965 (Box 8)
- Historic Pictures of Ireland: Album 1, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- The Hollins Critic, Hollins College, Virginia, October 1968 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Intireachas: The Policy of Poblacht Chriostuil, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Irish Coffee and Song with KYSOR, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Irish Coffee Preparation and Catering Photographs, undated (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Irish Pavilion: General, 1964-1980 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Irish Pavilion: Clippings from 1964 World's Fair (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Irish Pavilion: Clippings from Irish Pavilion on East 57th Street, 1960-circa 1979 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Irish Pavilion: Coffee Bar Menu, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Irish Pavilion: Correspondence Regarding Employment, Mar 1964-Apr 1964 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Irish Pavilion: Correspondence Regarding World's Fair, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Irish Pavilion: Invitation to Gala Opening, Jun 6, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Irish Pavilion: Photographs: General, undated (Box 7, Folder 13)
- Irish Pavilion: Photographs: 1964 World's Fair (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Irish Pavilion: Photographs: East 57th Street, after 1968 (Box 7, Folder 15)
- Irish Pavilion: Proclamation for Tenth Anniversary of The Irish Pavilion by President of the Council, City of New York, Dec 20, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Irish Pavilion: Products for Exhibition, Fall 1964 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Irish Pavilion: Recipes for an Irish Tea Party for Irish Export Board, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Irish Pavilion: Uniform Sketches and Notes, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Jim Downey's Steakhouse: Clippings, circa 1950-1977 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Jim Downey's Steakhouse: Correspondence, 1961-1967 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Jim Downey's Steakhouse: Postcards, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Jim Downey's Steakhouse: Stationary, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Notebooks, undated (Box 1, Folder 30-35)
- NYU Glucksman Ireland House: International Conference on Hunger, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Our Town Community Newspaper, Mar 14, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Panoramic Photograph: 75th Anniversary Dinner, County Armagh Men's P& B Association, Hotel Royal Manhattan, Oct 11, 1969 (Box AIAXOS001, Folder 1)
- Passports, 1953-1961 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Pipes and Drums of the Emerald Society, New York City Police Department Record, circa 1971 (Box 8)
- Playbill: Gate Theatre Presents Juno and the Paycock by Sean O'Casey, Jul 15, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Prayer Cards, 1945-1980 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Resume, undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Scrapbook [Disassembled], undated (Box 1, Folder 42-44)
- "A Short Story on the Parish Of Killure Fohenagh and Kilgerril," Tadgh MacLochlainn, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Slieve Bawn Handcraft Co-operative Supporters Dance, 1972, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- St. Patrick's Day Parade, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- "The Story of My Life in Ireland", circa 1990 (Box 1, Folder 48)